<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leekaize.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leekaize.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-31T15:30:13+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kai Ze’s Website</title><subtitle>Mechatronics major, researching in areas of IIoT, TinyML. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The AI Trap: How to Avoid Procrastination When Using Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/the-ai-trap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The AI Trap: How to Avoid Procrastination When Using Artificial Intelligence"/><published>2024-12-31T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-31T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/the-ai-trap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/the-ai-trap/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s the last day of 2024, and it feels fitting to reflect on the single word that has most impacted the world this year — AI. It has undeniably been a game-changer. However, I’ve noticed something unsettling within myself lately: an over-reliance on it. I’ve begun to feel like I’m outsourcing my thinking, and it’s turning me into a master procrastinator.</p> <h2 id="the-ai-procrastination-trap">The AI Procrastination Trap</h2> <p>AI is seductive. It gives you answers <em>fast</em>. Need a summary? Done. Need an outline? Boom. But this <strong>instant gratification</strong> started to replace the hard, focused thinking that leads to real understanding — the <strong>deep work</strong>.</p> <p>I’d spend hours tweaking AI outputs, feeling busy but not truly productive. It was like running on a hamster wheel. I’d get a decent essay written by an AI, but had I actually learned anything? Sure, it looked good, but where was <em>my</em> voice, <em>my</em> understanding?</p> <h2 id="my-aha-moment">My “Aha!” Moment</h2> <p>I realized I was using AI to avoid the tough stuff: creative thinking, problem-solving, the struggles that come with real learning. I was letting the machine do the heavy lifting, and my own mental muscles were dying.</p> <p>Here’s how I knew I was in trouble:</p> <ul> <li>Endless tweaking of AI-generated stuff without adding much of my own.</li> <li>Using AI as an escape whenever a task got challenging.</li> <li>A nagging feeling that my own thinking skills were getting rusty.</li> </ul> <h2 id="ai-friend-or-foe">AI: Friend or Foe?</h2> <p>The problem isn’t AI itself. It’s how I was using it. I needed to see it as a tool to <em>enhance</em> my work, not replace it.</p> <p>Now, when I open an AI tool, I stop and ask myself: “Why am I using this? How can it help me do <em>my</em> best work, not <em>do</em> the work for me?”</p> <p>One simple trick has been a game-changer. Before I ask AI to summarize something, I:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Skim it myself.</strong></li> <li><strong>Jot down my own quick summary.</strong></li> <li><strong>Then, and only then, see what the AI comes up with, and compare with mine.</strong></li> </ol> <p>This keeps me engaged and helps me actually learn.</p> <h2 id="getting-my-brain-back-in-gear">Getting My Brain Back in Gear</h2> <p>I’m retraining myself to focus and do the deep work I was avoiding. Here’s what’s helping:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Time Blocking:</strong> I schedule focused work time without AI.</li> <li><strong>Active Reading:</strong> I take notes, ask questions, and really engage with what I’m reading.</li> <li><strong>Handwritten Notes:</strong> Old school, but it works! Writing by hand helps me remember and understand better.</li> <li><strong>Reflection:</strong> I regularly check in with myself: Am I using AI as a tool or an escape?</li> </ul> <h2 id="using-ai-the-right-way-for-me">Using AI the Right Way (For Me)</h2> <p>AI can be a great brainstorming partner or help with outlines. And it’s a lifesaver for editing and proofreading. But it’s important to remember that we are still in control.</p> <p>I know others find AI a huge productivity booster. And that’s great! It’s about finding what works for <em>you</em>.</p> <h2 id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway</h2> <p>This whole experience has been a wake-up call. I’m learning to use AI intentionally, <strong>mindfully</strong>, so I can utilise its power without losing my own. It’s about rediscovering the joy of thinking for myself.</p> <p><strong>A small challenge:</strong> Resist the urge to immediately use an AI tool. Set a timer for 5-10 minutes and try to work on the task yourself before resorting to AI assistance. See how it feels.</p> <p>And yeah, this post was still touched up by AI. It’s a journey, and I’m still learning to find the right balance. Hopefully, my future posts will be even more genuinely me.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="ai,"/><category term="productivity,"/><category term="deep-work,"/><category term="mindfulness,"/><category term="technology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've realized that AI, while helpful, was turning me into a procrastinator. Here's how I'm taking back control and learning to use it as a tool, not a way to escape.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlock Your Blogging Potential with Jekyll: The Beauty of Static Sites</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/unlock-your-blogging-potential-with-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlock Your Blogging Potential with Jekyll: The Beauty of Static Sites"/><published>2024-12-25T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-25T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/unlock-your-blogging-potential-with-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/unlock-your-blogging-potential-with-jekyll/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-a-static-website">What is a Static Website?</h2> <p>Pre-built website that directly deliver to user when accessed, therefore:</p> <ul> <li>Fast—No one likes to wait, staring at a blank website.</li> <li>Secure—Simpler and has less attack surface for hacker.</li> </ul> <p>Noted: Static doesn’t mean no user interaction possible, you can still have comment sections, forms, or even interactive elements using JavaScript, but the core HTML structure is pre-built.</p> <h2 id="how-does-jekyll-makes-it-simple">How does Jekyll makes it simple?</h2> <ul> <li>Directly use markdown, not having to go through the messy HTML file.</li> <li>Use the community-support themes that suit your taste.</li> <li>Directly push it live on GitHub Pages for free!</li> </ul> <h2 id="what-are-the-overall-steps-of-building-jekyll-website">What are the overall steps of building Jekyll website?</h2> <p>It is essentially just some folder with some files:</p> <ul> <li>config files for some basic stuff</li> <li>content files in markdown</li> <li>template files for the looks of the site</li> </ul> <p>Jekyll will build the website from these source files.</p> <h2 id="how-to-deploy-to-github-pages">How to deploy to GitHub Pages?</h2> <p>We don’t have to take care of any server-side stuff, GitHub directly host all the final HTML, CSS etc. It’s all done in two steps:</p> <ul> <li>Create GitHub repository.</li> <li>Push the files to the repository.</li> <li>Use GitHub Actions to automate the process.</li> </ul> <h2 id="how-and-why-should-we-blog">How and why should we blog?</h2> <p>It’s an authentic way to get connected with people with same interests. We should make it a simple, non-tech-savvy place for sharing the thinking process and ideas. Remember the tech stuffs are just tools.</p> <p>We are all expert of our experiences, through the writing process, we organise our thoughts into something humanely resonates with others. Sharing what you experienced, the a-ha moments, not pretending to be some guru. And through this reflection, we often learn a lot for ourselves too.</p> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.taniarascia.com/make-a-static-website-with-jekyll/">Tania Rascia Article</a>. Utilising Jekyll with Sass and GitHub Pages.</li> <li><a href="https://karpathy.github.io/2014/07/01/switching-to-jekyll/">Andrej Karpathy Article</a>. Showing Jekyll advantages over Wordpress.</li> <li><a href="https://medium.com/@racheltho/why-you-yes-you-should-blog-7d2544ac1045">Rachel Thomas Article</a>. Showing how everyone has something to share, don’t keep those in your head.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="Jekyll"/><category term="Blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover How Jekyll Can Simplify Your Workflow and Help You Share Your Story]]></summary></entry></feed>