<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leekaize.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leekaize.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-07T10:21:26+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kai Ze’s Website</title><subtitle>Mechatronics major, researching in areas of IIoT, TinyML. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Using RSS to get or share ideas</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/using-rss-to-get-or-share-ideas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using RSS to get or share ideas"/><published>2025-04-07T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-07T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/using-rss-to-get-or-share-ideas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/using-rss-to-get-or-share-ideas/"><![CDATA[<p>For those who have never used RSS, it is a tool that allows us to subscribe to feeds from different sources: News, YouTube, Organisation Updates, Personal Blogs etc.</p> <p>It doesn’t push endless recommendations, competing for likes count, using tricks for better SEO, fulfill criterias to get promoted on specific platforms, etc.</p> <p>It simply serves the original intent of the Internet and social media, to share information to interested audience. And this is not even a “new technology”, RSS existed since 1999. It is the earlier, better, less corrupted form of social media.</p> <p>Many sources of information still support RSS and might even be reviving in the current trend of digital minimalist.</p> <p>To start using it, sign up for free RSS Aggregators. I would say <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a> is most frictionless one, just use their “Follow Sources” feature, find a blog/website you like, Subscribe to it then you’ll start receiving latest post in your feed. All of the YouTube channel can also be subscribed this way, just put their channel link there.</p> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/feedly-casey-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/feedly-casey-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/feedly-casey-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/feedly-casey.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Below are example of feeds. For YouTube, it will show just the video and description and nothing else.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/feedly-casey-post-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/feedly-casey-post-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/feedly-casey-post-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/feedly-casey-post.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/feedly-waitbutwhy-post-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/feedly-waitbutwhy-post-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/feedly-waitbutwhy-post-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/feedly-waitbutwhy-post.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>A good place to start reading is the Seth Godin’s Blog, it shows how a blog posts can be quick, yet deep, such as <a href="https://seths.blog/2025/04/an-eroding-sense-of-wonder/">his post</a> today.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ideas"/><category term="technology,"/><category term="ideas,"/><category term="knowledge"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore a life of using RSS as a primary information source.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Love?</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/what-is-love/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Love?"/><published>2025-02-14T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-14T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/what-is-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/what-is-love/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>An Open Letter to My Beloved Manda on Valentine’s Day</strong></p> <p>What is love? If we don’t have our own answer to this, what does it even mean when we tell our loved ones, “I Love You”?</p> <p>Love is not just about feeling good, not just a word you say, not merely an action, nor simply the willingness to sacrifice. Those are the results of love, but not its essence.</p> <p>Love is the ultimate force of living. You are the force that inspires me to embrace life to the fullest; we are the light that warms each other on our darkest days, and love is the deepest promise that we will never be alone.</p> <p>No matter what hardships life throws at us, we still run towards each other—actively, passionately, and steadfastly! We accept nature’s invitation and God’s calling, to share our hope and embrace every day.</p> <p>We will combine our strengths and complement one another. I strive to be not just someone with status, but a devoted father, a loving husband, and a caring son.</p> <ul> <li>Provide for our family, putting it before everything else.</li> <li>Protect you, ensuring that nothing in the world can hurt you.</li> <li>Lead our family towards our ultimate purpose and vision.</li> </ul> <p>Happy Valentine’s Day, my love.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="relationship,"/><category term="family"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We'll go through this life side by side, forever and ever <3]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Procrastinating with Note-Taking</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/procrastinating-with-note-taking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procrastinating with Note-Taking"/><published>2025-01-11T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-11T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/procrastinating-with-note-taking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2025/procrastinating-with-note-taking/"><![CDATA[<p>This had been an ongoing issue for me, for almost 10 years! Below are the insights and remedies inspired by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=baKCC2uTbRc">Sam Matla’s Video</a>.</p> <h2 id="the-personal-knowledge-management-hype">The Personal Knowledge Management Hype</h2> <p>It has become an almost must-have for the productivity gurus to talk about the “second brain”, of off-loading our knowledge in our brain, into a digital notebook or website. It all sounds great when you have this linkage between knowledge and can serve as a great foundation for future fusion of ideas.</p> <p>It started off ten years ago from Evernote to more features and better aesthetic Notion, to even more complex Obsidian, to scientifically backed Roam Research etc. It’s no longer focusing on storing knowledge, but rather on some minute details of optimising this process for a “perfect system”.</p> <h2 id="pkm-as-sophisticated-procrastination">PKM as Sophisticated Procrastination</h2> <p>It might be even worse than the clearer instant gratification procrastination, which can happen on over-reliance on AI in <a href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/procrastinating-with-ai/">my last blog post</a>.</p> <p>This kind of complicated second brain process can lead to self-pride of having a great system, and a sense of intellectual accomplishment, but there is no tangible result.</p> <p>When immersing in this system, we might even fall into the Collector’s Fallacy, accumulating vast amounts of notes, bookmarks, and highlights; creating a false sense of progress.</p> <h2 id="focus-on-work">Focus on Work</h2> <p>PKM is not work, trust our brain and put creativity as our most valuable asset. Project-based note-taking can be a good balance of work and documentation for future reference.</p> <p>Never be afraid of missing out on knowledge, there are so many things to explore every day, and you’ll never have enough time for EVERYTHING.</p> <p>The most important actionable step in my opinion: <strong>Choose a toolset that works, and stick with it for at least one year.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="ai,"/><category term="productivity,"/><category term="deep-work,"/><category term="mindfulness,"/><category term="technology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Prevent the pitfalls of Personal Knowledge Management system, or a so-called "second brain".]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Procrastinating with AI</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/procrastinating-with-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Procrastinating with AI"/><published>2024-12-31T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-31T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/procrastinating-with-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/procrastinating-with-ai/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s the last day of 2024, and it feels fitting to reflect on the single word that has most impacted the world this year — AI. It has undeniably been a game-changer. However, I’ve noticed something unsettling within myself lately: an over-reliance on it. I’ve begun to feel like I’m outsourcing my thinking, and it’s turning me into a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=arj7oStGLkU">master procrastinator</a>.</p> <h2 id="the-ai-procrastination-trap">The AI Procrastination Trap</h2> <p>AI gives you answers <em>fast</em>. Need a summary? Done. Need an outline? Boom. But this <strong>instant gratification</strong> started to replace the hard, focused thinking that leads to real understanding — the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f7V76Ky-_v8">deep work</a>.</p> <p>I’d spend hours tweaking AI outputs, feeling busy but not truly productive. It was like running on a hamster wheel. Sure, everything looked good, but where was <em>my</em> voice, <em>my</em> understanding?</p> <h2 id="so-how-to-use-ai">So, how to use AI?</h2> <p>The problem isn’t AI itself. It’s how I was using it. I needed to see it as a tool to <em>enhance</em> my work, not replace it.</p> <p>Now, often when I open an AI tool, I would stop and ask myself: “Why am I using this? How can it help me do <em>my</em> best work, not <em>do</em> the work for me?”</p> <p>Before I ask AI to summarize something, I:</p> <ol> <li>Skim it myself</li> <li>Jot down my quick summary</li> <li>Then, and only then, see what the AI comes up with, and compare it with mine</li> </ol> <p>This keeps me engaged and helps me learn.</p> <p>AI can be a great brainstorming partner or help with outlines. And it’s a lifesaver for editing and proofreading. But it’s important to remember that we are still in control.</p> <h2 id="the-takeaway">The Takeaway</h2> <p>I’m learning to use AI intentionally, <strong>mindfully</strong>, so I can utilize its power without losing my own. It’s often about re-discovering the joy of thinking for myself.</p> <p><strong>A small challenge:</strong> Resist the urge to immediately use an AI tool. Set a timer for 5-10 minutes and try to work on the task yourself before resorting to AI assistance. See how it feels.</p> <p>And yeah, this post was still touched up by AI. It’s a journey, and I’m still learning to find the right balance.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="ai,"/><category term="productivity,"/><category term="deep-work,"/><category term="mindfulness,"/><category term="technology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've realized that AI, while helpful, was turning me into a procrastinator. Here's how I'm taking back control and learning to use it as a tool, not a way to escape.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Beauty of Static Sites for Blogging</title><link href="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/the-beauty-of-static-sites-for-blogging/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beauty of Static Sites for Blogging"/><published>2024-12-25T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-25T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/the-beauty-of-static-sites-for-blogging</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leekaize.com/blog/2024/the-beauty-of-static-sites-for-blogging/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-a-static-website">What is a Static Website?</h2> <p>A pre-built website that directly delivers to the user when accessed, therefore:</p> <ul> <li>Fast: No one likes to wait, staring at a blank website.</li> <li>Secure: Simpler and has less attack surface for hackers.</li> </ul> <p>Noted: Static doesn’t mean no user interaction is possible. You can still have comment sections, forms, or even interactive elements using JavaScript, but the core HTML structure is pre-built.</p> <h2 id="how-does-jekyll-make-it-simple">How does Jekyll make it simple?</h2> <ul> <li>Use Markdown, there is no need to go through the messy HTML/CSS/JavaScript file.</li> <li>Use the community-support themes that suit your taste.</li> <li>Push it live on GitHub Pages for free!</li> </ul> <h2 id="overall-steps">Overall Steps</h2> <p>It is essentially just some folder with some files:</p> <ul> <li>Config files for some basic stuff</li> <li>Content files in Markdown</li> <li>Template files for the looks of the site</li> </ul> <p>Jekyll will build the website from these source files.</p> <h2 id="how-do-you-deploy-to-github-pages">How do you deploy to GitHub Pages?</h2> <p>We don’t have to take care of any server-side stuff, GitHub directly hosts all the final HTML, CSS, etc. It’s all done in two steps:</p> <ul> <li>Create a GitHub repository.</li> <li>Push the files to the repository.</li> <li>Use GitHub Actions to automate the process.</li> </ul> <h2 id="how-and-why-should-we-blog">How and why should we blog?</h2> <p>It’s an authentic way to get connected with people with the same interests. We should make it a simple, non-tech-savvy place for sharing the thinking process and ideas. Remember the tech stuffs are just tools.</p> <p>We are all experts in our experiences, through the writing process, we organize our thoughts into something that humanely resonates with others. Sharing what you experienced, the a-ha moments, not pretending to be some guru. Through this reflection, we often learn a lot for ourselves too.</p> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.taniarascia.com/make-a-static-website-with-jekyll/">Tania Rascia Article</a>. Utilizing Jekyll with Sass and GitHub Pages.</li> <li><a href="https://karpathy.github.io/2014/07/01/switching-to-jekyll/">Andrej Karpathy Article</a>. Showing Jekyll’s advantages over WordPress.</li> <li><a href="https://medium.com/@racheltho/why-you-yes-you-should-blog-7d2544ac1045">Rachel Thomas Article</a>. Showing how everyone has something to share, don’t keep those in your head.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="Jekyll"/><category term="Blogging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover How Jekyll Can Simplify Your Workflow and Help You Share Your Story]]></summary></entry></feed>